شران، بلدة ومركز ناحية تتبع منطقة عفرين شمال غرب حلب.
English Translation
Sharran, a town and sub-district center affiliated with the
Afrin district, northwest of Aleppo.
وقد بنيت بيوت البلدة على السفح الغربي لهضبة كلسية بارتفاع
500 متر فوق سطح البحر.
The houses of the town were built on the western slope of a
limestone plateau at an altitude of 500 meters above sea
level.
وهي تبعد عن مدينة عفرين 15 كيلومتراً باتجاه الشمال الشرقي.
It is 15 kilometers away from the city of Afrin towards the
northeast.
وبلدة شران مركز لناحية شران التي تزيد مساحتها عن 330
كيلومتراً مربعاً ويتبع لها 37 قرية و7 مزارع.
The town of Sharran is the center of the Sharran sub-
district, which has an area of more than 330 square
kilometers, and includes 37 villages and 7 farms.
يحدها شرقاً منطقة إعزاز، وغرباً حدود ناحيتي معبطلي وبلبل،
وأما شمالاً الحدود التركية السورية، وجنوباً بقية قرى مركز
الناحية.
It is bordered to the east by the Azaz district, to the west
by the borders of the Maabatli and Bulbul sub-districts, to
the north by the Syrian-Turkish border, and to the south by
the rest of the villages of the sub-district center.
قديماً كانت القرية غنية بالينابيع والآبار الرومانية.
In the past, the village was rich in springs and Roman
wells.
سكانها الأوائل من الكرد السوريين الذين ينتمون إلى عشيرة
شيكاكا، والذين قدموا إليها من جنوب شرق تركيا سابقاً، من
مدينة أورفا بالتحديد إضافة إلى عائلة عربية واحدة.
Its first inhabitants were Syrian Kurds belonging to the
Shikaka tribe, who previously came from southeastern Turkey,
specifically from the city of Urfa, in addition to one Arab
family.
يعيش فيها حالياً أكثر من 300 عائلة سورية من سكانها الأصليين
إضافة إلى عوائل سورية مهجرة قسراً من مناطق سورية مختلفة
وخاصة من محافظة حمص.
Currently, more than 300 Syrian families of its original
inhabitants live there, in addition to Syrian families
forcibly displaced from different Syrian regions, especially
from Homs governorate.
يعمل سكانها بالزراعة وخاصة زراعة الزيتون والعنب والرمان
والقمح والشعير والبقوليات. وفيها أكثر من 70 ألف شجرة زيتون.
Its residents work in agriculture, especially cultivating
olives, grapes, pomegranates, wheat, barley, and legumes. It
has more than 70,000 olive trees.
يوجد في البلدة مدارس حتى المرحلة الثانوية. وقد عرفت بالحفاظ
على التراث والفلكلور الشعبي الكردي.
There are schools in the town up to the secondary level. It
has been known for preserving Kurdish heritage and folklore.
واشتهرت بوجود فرقة شيكاكا للتراث والفلكلور الشعبي الكردي
فيها.
It is famous for having the Shikaka Band for Kurdish
Heritage and Folklore.
تقول الحكاية إن أهالي شران قدموا إلى هنا من جنوب شرق تركيا
من مدينة أورفا بالتحديد.
The story goes that the people of Sharran came here from
southeastern Turkey, specifically from the city of Urfa.
واستوطنوا بداية في خربة شران التي تبعد عن هنا 500 متر فقط في
الوادي وفي المغر المحيطة في هذا الوادي نظراً لكثرة المياه
والأحراش المحيطة فيها.
Initially, they settled in Khirbet Sharran, which is only
500 meters away from here, in the valley and the caves
surrounding this valley, due to the abundance of water and
the surrounding forests.
ثم حصل اقتتال مع الرعاة الذين حاولوا الاستيلاء على ينابيع
المياه وعلى أطراف الوادي، فانتقل أهالي شران إلى مكان البلدة
الحالية وسكنوا هنا.
Then fighting broke out with the shepherds who tried to
seize the water springs and the edges of the valley, so the
people of Sharran moved to the current location of the town
and settled here.
هناك قرابة بين أهالي خربة شران وبين أهالي شران.
There is a kinship between the people of Khirbet Sharran and
the people of Sharran.
لمعرفة المزيد عن تاريخ شران يسرنا أن يكون ضيفاً معنا العم
عبد المنان يوسف حسكو أبو يوسف، أحد أكبر الأشخاص العارفين
بتاريخ البلدة.
To learn more about the history of Sharran, we are pleased
to have as our guest Uncle Abdul Mannan Youssef Hasko Abu
Youssef, one of the eldest people knowledgeable about the
town's history.
تحياتي عمي أبو يوسف.
Greetings, Uncle Abu Youssef.
تسلم.
Thank you.
الله يعطيك العافية.
May God give you health.
الله يعافيك.
May God give you health too.
هلق هيدي اللي ورا خلفنا شو هيدي اللي هون؟
Now, what is this behind us here?
هي معصرة.
This is an olive press.
معصرة؟
An olive press?
معصرة في مغارة كانت؟
A primitive one.
Was it an olive press in a cave?
لا. لكا؟ معمار قناطر.
No. Why? It's arch architecture.
ما كانت مغارة هي.
It wasn't a cave.
طيب خلينا نمشي هيك نطلع باتجاه الساحة.
No.
Alright, let's walk this way and go towards the square.
شقد عمر هالضيعة؟
How old is this village?
عمر الضيعة حوالي 400 وكسور.
The village is about 400 and something years old.
400 وكسور؟
400 and something?
هون بس بالخربة 500.
Here, but in the Khirbeh, it's 500.
أه يعني الأصل بالخربة.
Ah, so the origin is in the Khirbeh.
بعدين انتقلوا لهون.
Then they moved here.
هدول انتقلتوا لهون.
They moved here.
احكي لي شوي عن تاريخها، عوائلها منين إجوا وكذا.
Tell me a little about its history, where its families came
from, and so on.
تاريخ تبعها كانوا ساحبين المواشي، واسمهم بالكردي كوتشار،
وبالعربي بدو رحل.
Regarding its history, they used to herd livestock, and they
are called Kochar in Kurdish, and Bedouin nomads in Arabic.
يروحوا ويجوا على البلاد، بكلف عليهم مشوار بعيد.
They would travel back and forth across the land, and it was
a long journey for them.
لوين يروحوا ويرجعوا؟
Where did they travel back and forth to?
على جنوب شرق تركيا، ما كان دولة عثمانية حاكمة المنطقة، ما
كان في حدود، ولا كان في دويلات. إيوه.
To southeastern Turkey. The Ottoman Empire was ruling the
region, there were no borders, and there were no small
states. Yes.
من هون لهون بعدها قاموا اتفقوا بركوا هون استوطنوا بالمغر
بخربة شران بالوادي.
Going back and forth, they eventually agreed to settle here
in the caves in Khirbet Sharran in the valley.
صار بينهم وبين رعاة اقتتال على جبل قطمة فوق.
A fight broke out between them and shepherds on Mount Qatma
above.
بدهم يجوا عالم بدهم يستولوا عليه وهدول ما خلوهم. قاموا على
بعضهم. نصبوا كمين للرعاة.
People wanted to come and take it over, but they didn't let
them. They fought each other. They set up an ambush for the
shepherds.
وبنص الليل بلشوا ببعضهم لشفاق الصبح.
And in the middle of the night, they started fighting each
other until the break of dawn.
بعدها صار فيهم قتلى كتير سموه وادي القتلى.
Afterwards, there were many casualties among them, so they
called it the Valley of the Dead.
وادي القتلى أو القتل أو الموت.
The Valley of the Dead, or killing, or death.
إيه، وادي القتلى هذا بين متينلي وبين خربة.
Yes, this Valley of the Dead is between Matinli and the
Khirbeh.
بالكردي بيقولوا كلي كوشتيا.
In Kurdish, they say "Gali Kushtiya".
نعم، إيوه.
Yes, exactly.
بعدها انتقلوا من هنيك لهون، قالوا هدول بجوز يجوا يقطعوا
بيننا وبين الماء.
Then they moved from there to here, they said these people
might come and cut us off from the water.
يقضوا علينا وعلى مواشينا.
And eliminate us and our livestock.
إجوا لهالطرف المي...
They came to this side of the water...
وبقي قسم هنيك.
And a group stayed there.
قال إذا إجوا هنن نحن من هالطرف وأنتم من طرف جنوبي بيناتنا...
They said if they come, we are on this side and you are on
the southern side, we surround them...
يعني بقي قسم في الخربة وقسم إجا لهون.
So a group stayed in the Khirbeh and a group came here.
إيوه.
Yes.
عمي أبو يوسف يعني هلق العشيرة اللي إجت لهون من جنوب شرق آسيا
هي شيكاكا، مو هيك؟
Uncle Abu Youssef, so the tribe that came here from
Southeast Asia is Shikaka, right?
إيش شو العوائل اللي هون؟
What are the families here?
العوائل كتروا.
The families have multiplied.
عدد لي إياهم كل الحاليا موجودين.
List all the ones currently present for me.
حاليا موجودين هلق بيت جلوسي، وبيت جوخدار، وبيت سيدو رشو،
وبيت دودخ، وبيت حسكو، وبيت هاشم، وبيت علي موسى، وبيت حمو
كان،
Currently present are the Jallousi family, Joukhadar family,
Sido Rasho family, Dodokh family, Hasko family, Hashem
family, Ali Mousa family, Hamou Kan family,
بيت عقلة،
Okla family,
بيت عقلة عرب.
The Okla family are Arabs.
إيه، بيت معدن، بيت حسكو، بيت الترك، بيت إينالو، بيت قرمان،
وبعدها تجمعت القرية مشكلة يعني.
Yes, Maadan family, Hasko family, Turk family, Inalo family,
Karaman family, and then the village gathered, it's a mix.
يعني عوائل كردية وعربية.
So, Kurdish and Arab families.
إيه مزبوط.
Yes, exactly.
حسك بيت حسك كمان.
Hasek, the Hasek family as well.
حسك هذول...
Hasek, these are...
من وين؟
From where?
يعني اسمه حسو بيسموه حسك.
I mean, his name is Hasso, they call him Hasek.
تمام تمام تمام. أنا أقصد إنه كان في عوائل كردية هون وعوائل
عربية.
Right, right, right. I mean that there were Kurdish families
here and Arab families.
لكا.
Of course.
هذا اللي بدي أقوله، كيف كان التعايش بيناتهم على مدى التاريخ؟
كيف كانوا عايشين مع بعض؟
That's what I want to say, how was the coexistence between
them throughout history? How did they live with each other?
عايشين متل إخوة، متل إخوة إخوة، في مصاهرة بيناتهم؟
Living like brothers, like real brothers. There is
intermarriage between them?
ما عرفنا تميز إلا بهالحرب.
We didn't know discrimination except in this war.
حقيقة ما عرفنا إلا بهالوقت.
Truly, we only knew it during this time.
في زواج ومصاهرة بيناتكم كمان؟
There is marriage and intermarriage among you too?
وكتير.
And a lot.
طيب العادات والتقاليد اللي بيناتكم اشتركت؟ يعني اختلطت
العادات العربية مع الكردية؟
Well, did the customs and traditions between you become
shared? I mean, did Arab customs mix with Kurdish ones?
هلق عم يحكوا بالكردي أحسن مني.
Now they speak Kurdish better than me.
وأنتم تحكوا عربي؟
And you speak Arabic?
لكا. تمام. إيه تمام.
Of course. Exactly. Yes, exactly.
الحياة كانت يعني بسيطة جداً وطبيعية، وفي محبة وفي ألفة
وبيوقفوا بجنب بعضهم، بالمناسبات، بالحزن، بالفرح.
Life was, I mean, very simple and natural, and there was
love and familiarity, and they stood by each other, on
occasions, in sadness, in joy.
إيمتى صارت هون مركز ناحية؟
When did this become a sub-district center?
مركز ناحية يمكن بـ 86. إيه 86.
A sub-district center, maybe in '86. Yes, '86.
صارت مركز ناحية.
It became a sub-district center.
إي والله.
Yes indeed.
تتبع لمنطقة عفرين.
Affiliated with the Afrin district.
هيدي راحت على فكري ما شفت الدفتر.
This slipped my mind, I didn't see the notebook.
ما في مشكلة. المهم إنه هي الآن هي مركز ناحية من نواحي منطقة
عفرين.
No problem. The important thing is that it is now a sub-
district center among the sub-districts of the Afrin
district.
أيوة.
Yes.
العلاقة هلق المسافة عن عفرين 13 كيلومتر؟
The relationship now... the distance from Afrin is 13
kilometers?
مو هيك؟ 15 أو 17. 15 أو 17.
Isn't it? 15 or 17. 15 or 17.
التعاون يعني المركز الإداري عندكم هو عفرين، أنتم بتروحوا على
عفرين بتسجلوا أولادكم وكذا. والعلاقة التجارية مع مين؟ إعزاز
ولا عفرين؟
The cooperation... I mean, your administrative center is
Afrin, you go to Afrin to register your children and so on.
Who is the commercial relationship with? Azaz or Afrin?
عفرين وإعزاز مشترك. عفرين وإعزاز. بنروح لعزاز علاقتنا بعزاز
من جد دور جدي أكتر من عفرين.
Afrin and Azaz are shared. Afrin and Azaz. We go to Azaz,
our relationship with Azaz is from my grandfather's time,
more than Afrin.
السبب ليش؟
What is the reason?
لأن عفرين جديدة، إعزاز قديم. قديم.
Because Afrin is new, Azaz is old. Old.
صحيح.
True.
طب هلق بدنا ندخل على بيت... على بيتكم اللي أنا بعرف إنه هو
من أقدم البيوت في القرية ونتعرف على نمط البناء فيه.
Well now, we want to enter a house... your house, which I
know is one of the oldest houses in the village, and learn
about its architectural style.
أهلاً وسهلاً تفضلوا.
Welcome, come in.
عمي أبو يوسف هلق هذا الجامع.
Uncle Abu Youssef, now this is the mosque.
إيوه.
Yes.
هذا الجامع؟
This is the mosque?
شرف.
Come in.
شقد عمر الجامع؟
How old is the mosque?
يعني 45، 45.
I mean 45, 45.
وهذا بيتكم.
And this is your house.
إيه.
Yes.
خلينا ندخل عالبيت.
Let's enter the house.
شرف.
Come in.
واضح هون المنطقة قديمة.
It's clear that the area here is old.
إيوه قديم جداً.
Yes, very old.
هلق وصلنا للبيت.
Now we've reached the house.
إيوه.
Yes.
هذا البيت هون مكتوب 1939.
This house here, it says 1939.
إيوه.
Yes.
هذا فعلاً عمره الحقيقي ولا بعرف أكتر من هيك؟
Is this really its true age, or do I know it's more than
that?
لا أقدم من هيك.
No, it's older than that.
اللي جوا.
The one inside.
اللي جوا أكتر.
The one inside is older.
قديش؟
How old?
شي 185 سنة.
About 185 years.
185 سنة. خلينا ندخل.
185 years. Let's enter.
خذنا طريق تفضلوا يا رب. يا رب. تفضلوا تفضلوا إن شاء الله يا
رب شرفوا. ندخل فورا؟
Let's take the path. Come in, oh Lord. Oh Lord. Come in,
come in, God willing, oh Lord, come in. Shall we enter right
away?
إيه، شرف.
Yes, come in.
البيت كم قسم هون يعني بني على كم مرحلة تاريخية؟
The house, how many sections are here? I mean, in how many
historical stages was it built?
مرحلة تاريخية، هذا 39، هي تاريخها يمكن بـ 1800 وشوي. وهديك
بـ 1964 ما تبقى كمالة.
A historical stage, this one is '39. That one's date is
maybe 1800 and something. And that one is 1964, the rest is
an addition.
يعني معناها 39 و 64 وهيدي أقدم شي.
That means '39 and '64, and this is the oldest part.
إيه، هذا هو.
Yes, that's it.
هون بيت اللي كان الجد... هون بيت الجد هون.
Here is the house where the grandfather was... the
grandfather's house is here.
أبو جد لسع.
My grandfather's father actually.
أبو جدك هاد كان بيته.
This was your great-grandfather's house.
طيب خلينا ندخل نشوف.
Alright, let's go in and take a look.
Zeno, were kakê were kakê.
Zeno, come brother, come brother.
يلا، هلأ عمي أبو يوسف نحن الآن رح ندخل على أقدم قسم في
بيتكم، اللي عم تقول إنت عمره شي 180 سنة؟
Let's go. Now, Uncle Abu Youssef, we are about to enter the
oldest part of your house, which you say is about 180 years
old?
185.
185، تفضلوا.
185, please come in.
يا رب.
Oh God.
شغل الأضوية.
Turn on the lights.
عمي أبو يوسف هلأ هاد البيت هاد عم تقولي عمره 185 سنة، هلأ
هاد السقف من الخشب... هاد فعلا هاد هو نفسه؟
Uncle Abu Youssef, you're telling me this house is 185 years
old. Now, this wooden roof... is this really the original
one?
نفسه هو.
It's the same one.
ما تغير؟
It hasn't been changed?
لا لا لا، من 185 سنة.
No, no, no, since 185 years ago.
بس هيديك السنة ابني يوسف جاب السيبا وليفة واسفنجة وشو اسمه
ومي وصابون غسل الخشبات.
But last year, my son Youssef brought a ladder, a loofah, a
sponge, water, and soap, and he washed the wood.
هاد الخشب من أي خشب هاد، حور هاد شو هاد؟
What kind of wood is this? Is it poplar? What is it?
حور هذا حور.
Poplar, this is poplar.
هذا حور جابوه من جبل كاور داغ. جبال طوروس هدول بيقولوا
بالعربي اللي عليهم ثلج من تركيا، هداك الوقت ما كان في حدود.
Okay.
هذا حور جابوه من جبل كاور داغ. جبال طوروس هدول بيقولوا
بالعربي اللي عليهم ثلج من تركيا، هداك الوقت ما كان في حدود.
This is poplar, they brought it from the Gavur Dağı
mountain. The Taurus Mountains, as they call them in Arabic,
the ones with snow in Turkey. At that time, there were no
borders.
من جبال... على ظهر الجمال جابوهن.
Yes.
From the mountains... they brought them on the backs of
camels.
طيب، هذا البيت قوس...
Alright, this house is a single arch...
أيوا.
Yes.
قوس واحد مو هيك؟ وفجتين.
One arch, right? And two vaults.
فجتين وقوس واحد.
Two vaults and one arch.
إي، في بعض منهم هون عامود... قنطرة وقنطرة لهداك طرف وتلت
فجات.
Yes, in some of them, there is a pillar here... an archway,
an archway on the other side, and three vaults.
نعم. خلي وجهك ع الكاميرا لو سمحت بس.
Yes. Just keep your face towards the camera, please.
وهذا كلين، هدول لإيش؟
And this is a kilim, what are these for?
هدول حجرات... أولي بيت واحد كانوا بيجيبوا عروس، بيربطوا هون
وهون، بيقولوا كجية.
These are stones... in the past, it was a single room. When
they brought a bride, they would tie them here and here,
they call it a "Kejiye".
بيصنعوا النسوان أربع أصابيع عرضهم، وبيزينوه بشو اسمه... هدول
ايش بتسموهن التت تبع العرب... إيوا هيك...
Women make it, four fingers wide, and decorate it with...
what do you call the things Arabs use... yes, like that...
دانتيلا أو كذا.
Lace or something.
إي... من الأول... بيجوزوا مثلاً بتيجي عروس بيزتوا عليه
برداية، العروس هون بتتجوز ووحدة هون بتتجوز...
Yes... from the past... For example, if someone gets married
and a bride comes, they throw a curtain over it. One bride
gets married here, and another gets married here...
كل واحد ببيت يعني قصدك؟
You mean each one in a separate room?
إي هدول هنن، وهي العتبة للكل كان، بيغسلوا فيها.
Yes, these are them. And this threshold was for everyone,
they would wash in it.
هون كانوا يبركوا رجال وهون نسوان؟
Did men sit here and women sit here?
هون رجال، هي صفاية للرجال.
Men here, this was a heater for men.
دفاية، مدفأة إي شو مانع نرفع وشيل البرداي؟
A heater, a stove. Yes, what's stopping us from lifting and
removing the curtain?
إي منشيله خلص مبين.
We'll remove it, it's already visible.
بدي أسألك سؤال بس بسيط إنه هون في أدوات يعني كلها نحاسية
واضح قديمة إلها علاقة بتاريخ هاد البيت. في هون لفت نظري شغلة
بس هي... هاد شو هاد؟
I just want to ask a simple question. There are copper tools
here, clearly old, related to the history of this house.
Something here caught my attention... What is this?
هاد زمان أول... ما كان في مغاسل، في هالإبريق وفي هي اسمها
بالتركي إيل يغني (el leğeni). يعني المغسل اليدوي.
This is from the old days... there were no sinks. There was
this jug and this thing called "el leğeni" in Turkish,
meaning a manual washbasin.
نعم.
Yes.
بيجي الضيف بيبرك عالدشك هيك... ما في مغسلة برا كذا، صابونة
هون، إيوا لازم كنا حطينا صابونة.
A guest comes and sits on the mattress like this... there's
no sink outside or anything, a soap is here... yes, we
should have put a soap.
ما في مشكلة.
No problem.
إي، وأصغر واحد بالبيت بيصب المي، إذا شتي مي سخنة وإذا صيف مي
باردة، والبشكير على كتفه، بعد ما غسل بيعطي بشكير بينشف إيديه
وبيبرك على الدشك تبعه، هاد الضيف معزز مكرم.
Yes, and the youngest person in the house pours the water.
Hot water in winter, and cold water in summer, with a towel
on his shoulder. After washing, he hands the towel, the
guest dries his hands and sits on his mattress. The guest is
honored and respected.
الله يعطيكم العافية، ما شاء الله عليك.
May God give you strength, God bless you.
إيوا، فلذلك هي من تراث جد أبوي.
Yes, therefore, this is from my great-grandfather's
heritage.
جد أبوك، قد ايش عمرها هي 200 سنة؟
Your great-grandfather, how old is this? 200 years?
هو عاش 115 سنة، ومن 63 متوفي.
He lived to be 115 years old, and he died in '63.
الله يرحمه.
May God have mercy on him.
إيش قد صار عمرها هي؟ 115 و 63... وهلأ نحن بالـ 21، كمان
62...
How old is this now? 115 and 63... and now we are in '21,
plus 62...
ما شاء الله، يعني شي 200 سنة.
Mashallah, so it's about 200 years old.
100... يعني 175 تقريباً.
100... I mean roughly 175.
إيوا...
Yes...
عمي أبو يوسف الله يعطيك العافية.
Uncle Abu Youssef, may God give you strength.
احتفظنا فيه كتراث.
We kept it as a heritage.
الله يعطيك العافية، شكراً إلك.
May God give you strength, thank you.
تسلم، حياكم الله، أهلاً وسهلاً.
Bless you, God greet you, welcome.
أهل شيكاك معروفين بحبهم وعشقهم للتراث والفلكلور الكردي. لهيك
هنن بيعرفوا كل الرقصات والدبكات المشهورة بمنطقة عفرين،
وبسوريا بعموم سوريا كمان.
The people of Shikak are known for their love and passion
for Kurdish heritage and folklore. That's why they know all
the famous dances and dabkes in the Afrin region, and in
Syria as a whole.
لهيك بعام 2000 ساووا فرقة اسمها فرقة شيكاك للفلكلور الشعبي
الكردي واللي شاركت بالعديد من المهرجانات الداخلية والخارجية،
وحازت على أكثر من جائزة، ولكن بسبب ظروف الحرب بسوريا توقفت
بكل أسف.
That is why in the year 2000, they formed a group called the
Shikak Troupe for Kurdish Folk Folklore, which participated
in many domestic and international festivals and won more
than one award. But unfortunately, due to the war in Syria,
it was stopped.
حتى نتعرف على هالفرقة وعلى الفلكلور الشعبي الكردي في شران،
رح نتعرف ونحكي مع رئيس الفرقة، أبو عبدو، عبد الرحمن ترك عمر،
وباقي عدد من أفراد الفرقة.
To get to know this group and the Kurdish folk folklore in
Sharran, we will meet and talk with the head of the troupe,
Abu Abdo, Abdul Rahman Turk Omar, and a number of other
members of the troupe.
الله يعطيك العافية أبو عبدو.
May God give you health, Abu Abdo.
الله يعافيك.
May God give you health.
احكيلي شوي هيك يعني عن الفلكلور هون، الفلكلور الغنائي
والشعبي، الدبكات، الرقصات، اللي بتميز أهل شران.
Tell me a bit about the folklore here. The musical and
popular folklore, the dabkes, the dances that distinguish
the people of Sharran.
قمنا بالتراث القديم إلنا للأكراد، يعني التراث، قمنا فيها
وحفظنا فيها إنه ليش هالتراث ما يضيع، يتم للجيل اللي بعدنا.
وعم نتابع فيها، عم ندبك واسم الرقصات واسم الأغاني واسم الكل
يعني عندنا هون.
We revived our old Kurdish heritage, I mean the heritage, we
revived it and preserved it so that this heritage would not
be lost and would remain for the generation after us. And we
are continuing with it, we dabke, and we know the names of
the dances and the names of the songs and the names of
everything here.
عندي في البيت أنا عم أتحافظ عليها على حيل الله وقت. وهلأ
أنتم جيتوا وأنا مستعد أقدم لكم كل الأغاني وكل شو اسمه...
وأنتم جيتوا وأهلاً وسهلاً فيكم وفي حلب اليوم.
I keep them in my house to preserve them at all times. And
now you have come, and I am ready to present to you all the
songs and everything... You came and you are welcome here
and in Aleppo today.
الله يكرمك عمي أبو عبدو، سؤالي أنا سؤالي، الفلكلور اللي هون،
الدبكات والرقصات الشعبية بتختلف شي عن باقي عفرين؟ يعني شران
الفلكلور تبعها بيختلف عن باقي عفرين ولا لأ مثل عفرين؟
May God honor you, Uncle Abu Abdo. My question is, does the
folklore here, the dabkes and the folk dances, differ from
the rest of Afrin? Does Sharran's folklore differ from the
rest of Afrin or is it the same?
في منهم بيختلفوا، في منهم ما بيختلفوا.
Some of them differ, some don't.
طيب ايش هو الشي اللي بيميز أهل شران؟
Alright, what distinguishes the people of Sharran?
ها ها... في منهم هدول نحن قريبين عن حدود تركيا كان. عايفين
منهم كم لقطة دبكة من تبع تركيا. مو الأول كانوا عثمانيين
بتركيا، إجوا جماعة الكراد من هنيك لهون، تفرقوا من بعضهم،
صاروا يحكوا على دبكة باللغة التركية، سمينا هون بالنسبة مثلاً
اسمها بتيجي عالتركي مو عالكردي.
Haha... some of them... we used to be close to the Turkish
borders. We have some dabke moves from Turkey. In the past,
there were Ottomans in Turkey, a group of Kurds came from
there to here, they separated from each other, they started
calling the dabke in the Turkish language. We named them
here, for example, their names are in Turkish, not Kurdish.
مثل إيش؟ عطيني مثال.
Like what? Give me an example.
مثل مثلاً هونه... شو اسمه... ياغلق كينار (yağlık kenar).
Like, for example... what's it called... Yağlık Kenar.
دوقوزلو (dokuzlu)... هدول بالتركي.
Dokuzlu... these are in Turkish.
آلاي (alay).
Alay.
يعني هدول دبكات كردية لكن مشتركة مع الأتراك كان أولي،
أخذت...
So these are Kurdish dabkes but were shared with the Turks
in the past, they were taken...
جبناها لهون، وعم نحافظين فيها هلأ.
We brought them here, and we are preserving them now.
ما زلتوا... وأنتم تحفظوا كل هاد التراث؟
Are you still... and do you preserve all this heritage?
كله حافظانه.
We've memorized all of it.
بالموسيقى، بالدبكات، بالإيقاعات، بالأغاني، حتى باللباس.
With the music, the dabkes, the rhythms, the songs, even the
clothing?
صح.
Right.
طيب... تحكيلي عن الفرقة شوي، ايمتى تأسست؟
Alright... tell me a little about the troupe. When was it
founded?
الفرقة أسسناها نحن بالـ 2000. كان معنا جماعة هون بالضيعة نحن
فرقة، كان تبع الضيعة. يعني سويناها أول شي كان كم واحد نحن عم
ندبك بالأعراس وبالشغلات.
We founded the troupe in 2000. We had a group of people here
in the village, we were a troupe, it belonged to the
village. I mean, we first started as a few guys doing dabke
at weddings and things.
قلنا لخيو خلينا نساوي لنا فرقة. سوينا فرقة، بلشنا فيها و...
قدمنا قدمنا، الحمد لله، ورحنا عالمهرجانات وعلى حفلات، وين ما
رحنا الحمد لله تيسرنا يعني.
We said, let's form a troupe for ourselves. We formed a
troupe, started it and... we presented, thank God, and we
went to festivals and parties, wherever we went, thank God
we were successful.
والفرقة مشيت لحد الـ... قبل الثورة. والأخ أبو روني ساعدنا
بالخياطة، إيوا... تكميل هي هو يحكي لنا عن... لبس الفرقة.
And the troupe kept going until... before the revolution.
And brother Abu Roni helped us with the tailoring. Yes...
the completion of it, he will tell us about the troupe's
clothes.
طيب، هلأ أنتم شاركتوا بمهرجانات داخلية وخارجية، شاركتوا
بحلب، شاركتوا بدمشق، شاركتوا بالعراق، وهيك...
Okay, now you've participated in domestic and international
festivals. You participated in Aleppo, you participated in
Damascus, you participated in Iraq, and so on...
رحنا بالعراق، أول شي بالعراق بالسليمانية، قدمنا مهرجان، يعني
مشي حال معنا هنيك، وجينا أخذنا جائزة، أخذنا كل شي، الحمد لله
ماشي حالنا.
We went to Iraq, first we went to Iraq, to Sulaymaniyah, we
presented at a festival. I mean, things went well for us
there, and we came back and won an award, we won everything,
thank God we are doing well.
خليني أنتقل لأبو روني، وأسأله سؤال عن موضوع اللباس، أبو
روني، الله يعطيك العافية.
Let me move on to Abu Roni and ask him a question about the
clothing. Abu Roni, may God give you health.
أهلاً وسهلاً فيكم.
Welcome to you.
تحكيلي عن اللباس، أنا اللي فهمته إنه أنت خياط الفرقة. يعني
هذا اللباس اللي لابسينه الآن، أبو عبدو وأبو يوسف وحضرتك، هو
خياطتك أنت. تحكيلي عن أجزاءه، تفاصيله.
Tell me about the clothing. What I understand is that you
are the tailor of the troupe. I mean, these clothes you are
wearing now, you, Abu Abdo, and Abu Youssef, you tailored
them. Tell me about their parts and details.
هيدا بنسميه نحن بالكردي yan targ، بالعربي نصية اسمها. اسمها
yan targ. قميص أبيض عادي، والسروال.
This we call "yan targ" in Kurdish. In Arabic, it's called a
half-shirt. Its name is yan targ. A regular white shirt, and
the sirwal.
وهيدي...
And this...
قشط...
A belt...
Pişt.
بالعربي شال إي...
In Arabic, a shawl. Yes...
بالعربي شال. وهاد طاسوم (tasum)...
In Arabic, a shawl. And this is a tasum...
طاسومة بالعربي؟
A tasoumeh in Arabic?
إي طاسوم. بالكردي filar.
Yes, tasum. In Kurdish, "filar".
طيب، أنا سؤالي هلأ هاد بيتميز عن اللبس العربي أو الشامي أو
الحلبي؟ في اختلاف شي بسيط؟
Okay, my question is, does this differ from the Arab,
Levantine, or Aleppine dress? Is there a slight difference?
شو الاختلاف؟ الاختلاف الشروال الكردي من هون... من عند
الرجل... سرجو قصير. الشامي بيجي طويل.
What's the difference? The difference is the Kurdish sirwal
from here... from the leg... the crotch is short. The
Levantine one is long.
هداك الدوماني... الدوماني بيجي طويل هيك، هاد بيجي قصير.
The Doumani one... The Doumani one is long like this, this
one is short.
الله يعطيك العافية. برجع لعند أبو عبدو وبسأله سؤال بس بسيط
قبل ما نشوف أنواع الدبكات تبعكم، حط على راسك هذا الطربوش
خليني أسميه.
May God give you health. I'll go back to Abu Abdo and ask
him just a simple question before we see your types of
dabkes. Put this tarboosh, let me call it, on your head.
إيوا...
Yes...
هي شو قصتها هاي؟ مطعوجة هيك لفوق...
What's the story behind this? Folded upwards like this...
Kumê sivik an jî dibêjin kumê qulik...
Kumê sivik, or they say kumê qulik...
شو يعني احكيلي بالعربي.
What does that mean? Tell me in Arabic.
هي القبوعة... أبيض بنقول له، واللي فوقه هاد مبخوش. إي طربوش
المبخوش.
This is the hat... we call it the white one, and the top of
it is pierced. Yes, the pierced tarboosh.
Ya'nî ismu bi-Kurdî kum.
So its name in Kurdish is kum.
Tamam, ya'nî, ya'nî lêş şâr bi-haza ş-şekil? Lêş ma şâr
meselan bi-şekil ṭaqiye?
Kum.
Tamam, ya'nî, ya'nî lêş şâr bi-haza ş-şekil? Lêş ma şâr
meselan bi-şekil ṭaqiye?
Okay, so, so why is it made in this shape? Why wasn't it
made like a taqiye (small cap), for example?
Aha... hay bi-ayyâm el-awwal bi-z-zaman... ya'nî el-fellaḥîn
yrûḥû 'a l-fellaḥ yrûḥû yḥoṭṭû 'a râson.
Aha... this in the old days, in the past... I mean the
farmers used to go to farm, they put it on their heads.
Kân yşîr denya şob metl ma 'am tqûl, kân şû ismo, yşîlû şway
hayk yâxod nafas.
The weather would get hot, as you say, they would... lift it
a bit like this to take a breath.
Bi-râso...
With his head...
Wa fî şî tânî meselan... W huwa... metl şû ismo kân el-
Êzîdiyîn el-awwaliyîn...
And there is another thing, for example... And it's... like
what was it called, the early Yezidis...
El-Êzîdiyîn el-awwaliyîn, ewe.
The early Yezidis, yes.
Aywa, kânû ysamû hay qubbê taba' eş-şû ismo... Ziyara
taba'on.
Yes, they used to call this the dome of... what was it
called... Their shrine.
Laliş.
Lalesh.
Qubbet Laliş.
The Dome of Lalesh.
Aywa, qubbet Laliş, aywa!
Yes, the Dome of Lalesh, exactly!
Hay teşbaḥ, ya'nî şabaḥ.
This resembles it, I mean it's similar.
Tamam, tamam, tamam. Hada?
Okay, okay, okay. This?
Hay desmal.
This is a desmal.
Ya'nî mendîl?
You mean a handkerchief?
Mendîl, eh.
A handkerchief, yes.
Alwânu min wayn ma'xûza?
Where are its colors taken from?
Alwân 'adiye... 'anna hon bi-l-Akrâd ya'nî, sor, spî, zer...
Normal colors... here among us Kurds I mean, red, white,
yellow...
Alwân eṭ-ṭabî'a wa-l-mojtama'?
The colors of nature and society?
Ṭabî'a, mojtama', 'a l-kull şî...
Nature, society, for everything...
Tamam, tamam.
Okay, okay.
Xallînî halla' şûf iza ma'na waqt, bi-tlêt daqayeq arba'
daqayeq... nşûf anwa' ed-dabkêt illî momkin torqoṣûha
halla'.
Let me see now if we have time, in three or four minutes...
let's see the types of dances that you can perform now.
Wa illî hiye txoṣṣ el-manṭaqa. Wa hiye aydan folklôr Kurdî.
And which are specific to the region. And it is also Kurdish
folklore.
Ṣaḥ.
True.
Tfaḍḍal.
Go ahead.
Yalla, inşallah.
Alright, hopefully.
Allah ye'aṭîkum el-'âfiye. Tfaḍḍalû.
May God give you health. Go ahead.
Halla' awwal raqṣa raqaṣtûha...
Now the first dance you performed...
Aywa.
Yes.
Awwal weḥde, awwal dawre... şû m-sammîha hayde?
The first one, the first round... what do you call this?
Hada ismu Mewlânî.
This is called Mewlanî.
Mewlânî.
Mewlanî.
Ya'nî hay tarḥîb?
Yes.
So this is a welcoming?
Hay tarḥîb. Awwal ma bet-fût 'ala şû ismo... 'ala masraḥ,
şağalêt... bet-emşî fîha hay er-raqṣa.
This is a welcoming. As soon as you enter what's it
called... on a stage, things... you walk in this dance.
Bet-şûf el-jomhûr, bet-ḥayyî el-jomhûr.
You look at the audience, you greet the audience.
Er-raqṣa l-ba'da?
The dance after that?
L-ba'da Çîftetelî kênat, eh?
The one after it was Çîftetellî, wasn't it?
Eh, Çîftetelî hay bi-t-Turkî.
Yes, Çîftetellî, this is in Turkish.
Ya'nî el-ma'na ilo...
So its meaning is...
Tentên. Ḥaraktên, eh. Bi-ḥaraktên, aywa.
Two. Two movements, yes. With two movements, exactly.
Ḥaraktên ma' ba'd... Amma r-raqṣa t-têlte?
Two movements together... And what about the third dance?
Er-raqṣa t-têlte, hada kamên bi-t-Turkî, Dokuzlu. Tes'a
ya'nî. Tes' ḥarakêt.
The third dance, this is also in Turkish, Dokuzlu. Meaning
nine. Nine movements.
Wâḥed etnên tlête... Tlête bi-tlête bi-tlête... Wa fîha
qafez, aywa.
One, two, three... Three by three by three... And it has
jumping, yes.
Hadol kellon Kurdiyêt? Muştarakêt bi-t-turâs wa-l-folklôr
el-Kurdî wa-l-'Arabî?
Are these all Kurdish? Shared in the Kurdish and Arab
heritage and folklore?
Ṣaḥ.
True.
W dâxilêt ma' ba'd.
And they are intertwined together.
Ṣaḥ, kellon... Hadol el-anğêm ya'nî kellon ma' ba'don...
True, all of them... These melodies are all with each
other...
Şarqî ya'nî, 'êyşîn sawa.
Oriental, meaning, we live together.
Ktîr. Allah ye'aṭîkum el-'âfiye. Ahla wa sahla.
A lot. May God give you health. Welcome.
Şukran ilkun, şukran.
Thank you, thank you.
Ed-dolma we-s-sorma we-l-yalanjî, ya'nî el-maḥşî we-l-
yabraq... aklêt şa'biye ktîr maşhûra bi-manṭaqat Efrîn.
Dolma, sorma, and yalanji, meaning stuffed vegetables and
stuffed grape leaves... are very famous traditional dishes
in the Afrin region.
Wa aydan fî Şerrân. Xâṣatan bi-hay el-fatra, illî fîha waraq
el-'enab fî waqt el-qiṭâf.
And also in Sherran. Especially in this period, when grape
leaves are in picking season.
Xaltî Um Yûsif raḥ enzûra, 'am toṭboxna l-yom ed-dolma, el-
maḥşî,
We will visit Auntie Um Youssef, she is cooking dolma today,
the stuffed vegetables,
wa aydan 'am teḍrob el-jibne min ḥalîb el-mâ'ez wa-l-ğanam.
and she is also making cheese from goat and sheep's milk.
Raḥ enzûra la-nşûf kîf ṭabxet el-maḥşî w şû bet-ḥoṭṭ-lo, wa
aydan şû raḥ es-sawî be-l-jibne. Tâbe'ûna.
We will visit her to see how she cooked the stuffed
vegetables and what she puts in them, and also what she will
do with the cheese. Follow us.
As-salâmu 'alaykum.
Peace be upon you.
'Alaykum as-salâm.
Peace be upon you too.
Xaltî Um Yûsif şlonik?
Auntie Um Youssef, how are you?
El-ḥamdulillah... ahlen wa sahlen.
Thank God... welcome.
Allah ye'aṭîkî el-'âfiye.
May God give you health.
Allah ye'âfîk.
May God give you health too.
'Am teṭboxî el-maḥşî.
You are cooking stuffed vegetables.
Ewa.
Yes.
Farjîna şû ṭabaxtî w şû saweytî... tfaḍḍal.
Show us what you cooked and what you made... go ahead.
Ahla wa sahla, tfaḍḍalû.
Welcome, go ahead.
Bayt baytkun.
Make yourselves at home.
Allah yesallmak. Hay...
May God keep you safe. This...
Waqfî min hon, law samaḥtî... iwa. Eh, eḥkî-lna.
Stand here, please... yes. Yeah, tell us.
Saweyt maḥşî l-kun.
I made stuffed vegetables for you.
Maḥşî, eh.
Stuffed vegetables, yeah.
W saweyt, ğaleyt farrûj.
And I made, I boiled a chicken.
Kamên meşên-kun n-sawî frîke, soxne.
Also for you, so we make hot freekeh.
Ya'nî farrûj w frîke, wa-l-maḥşî, illî entû bet-sammûh...
So chicken and freekeh, and stuffed vegetables, which you
call...
Meşên eḍ-ḍyûf.
For the guests.
Allah yekremek.
May God bless you.
Ahla w sahla 'ala râsna.
Welcome, you are very dear to us.
Allah yesallem râsek ya rabb. Halla' hada huwe d-dolma?
May God keep you safe, oh Lord. Now, is this the dolma?
Aywa.
Yes.
Min şû ṭabaxtî... hada borğol wella ruz?
What did you cook it with... is this bulgur or rice?
Lâ, be-r-ruz.
No, with rice.
Şû bet-ḥoṭṭî-lo?
What do you put in it?
Laḥme... wa tom, wa bharât, ays ma baddak.
Meat... and garlic, and spices, whatever you want.
Şû s-sabab illî... ya'nî ed-dolma aw el-maḥşî maşhûra ktîr
bi-manṭaqat Efrîn, layş?
What is the reason that... I mean, dolma or stuffed
vegetables are very famous in the Afrin region, why?
Akle şa'biye ktîr.
It's a very traditional dish.
Kwayyes, eh.
Good, yeah.
Kwayyese, laḥme ya'nî... ṭabxa hayk aṣliye. Min qadîme.
It's good, meat, you know... such an authentic dish. From
the old times.
Qadîme ya'nî taqlîdiye.
Old, meaning traditional.
Lakan.
Of course.
Ṭayyib, şû illî bi-mayyeza 'ankun hon meselan 'an Ḥalab?
Okay, what distinguishes it here for you from Aleppo, for
example?
Wallah ṭabxatna ya'nî nafs eş-şî ṭab'an metl Ḥalab. Mû neḥna
'êyşîn ktîr b-Ḥalab?
Well, our dish is basically the same as Aleppo's, of course.
Haven't we lived a lot in Aleppo?
W kel ṭabxatna ya'nî bet-şûfîha 'a-Ḥalab.
And all our dishes, I mean, you see them based on Aleppo's
style.
Ana ba'ref inno ahl Ḥalab byoṭobxû l-maḥşî be-l-borğol.
I know that the people of Aleppo cook stuffed vegetables
with bulgur.
Eh, hayk w hayk b-sawû.
Yes, they do it both ways.
Entû bet-sawû kamên hayk?
Do you do it like that too?
Lakan. Frîke, w ḥommoṣ, w y-kûn ḥadde,
Of course. Freekeh, and chickpeas, and it has to be spicy,
W yḥoṭṭû-lon laḥme kamên, nafs eş-şî.
And they put meat in it too, the same thing.
Bas ana mara kbîre, ma baḥsen saweyî no'ên ya'nî, saweyt no'
wâḥed.
But I'm an old woman, I can't make two types, you know, I
made one type.
Allah yşeddek be-l-'âfiye ya rabb.
May God give you strength and health, oh Lord.
Allah ye'âfîk.
May God give you health too.
Ana ba'ref kamên aydan ahl Ḥalab wa bâqî el-manâṭeq byâklû
janb el-maḥşî el-ḥâmmoḍ, mayyet el-ḥâmmoḍ taba'a...
I also know that the people of Aleppo and other regions eat
the sour broth next to the stuffed vegetables, its sour
broth...
Eh fî mayyet ḥâmmoḍ, w ayrân...
Yes, there is sour broth, and ayran...
Ayrân...
Ayran...
W flayfle... w ays ma baddak.
And peppers... and whatever you want.
Ṭayyib halla' şû ḥâṭeṭayle tatqîle hay?
Okay, now what is this weight you put on it?
Eh tatqîle şû be-sammûha hay?
Yeah, weight, what do they call this?
Hay hâwan.
This is a mortar.
Hâwan, eh.
A mortar, yeah.
'Am bet-taqlî l-maḥşî.
You are weighing down the stuffed vegetables.
Meşên ma yaṭla' minno l-may.
So the water doesn't come out of it.
Aywa.
I see.
Tamam... şqad badda ḥatta ya'nî testewî?
Alright... how long does it take until, you know, it's fully
cooked?
Wallah sâ'a w hayk ya'nî, iza nâr qaweye sâ'a, sâ'a w noṣ
bet-ṣîr.
Well, an hour or so, you know, if the fire is strong, it
takes an hour, an hour and a half.
Awwalî kentû t-ṭobxû 'a-l-xaşab? 'A-l-ḥaṭab?
In the past, did you use to cook on wood? On firewood?
Ma baḥsen.
I can't.
Awwal eh?
In the past, yes?
Awwal eh.
In the past, yes.
Halla' 'a-l-ğâz saweytû kamên.
Now you've made it on the gas stove too.
Halla' kamên.
Now too.
Lakan.
Of course.
Bas ana mara kbîre w marḍâne...
But I'm an old woman and sick...
Salâmtek, 'azzabnâkî.
Get well soon, we've bothered you.
Allah yesallmak. Ma'layş.
May God keep you safe. It's okay.
'Azzabnâkî r-râḥa.
We've bothered your comfort.
Allah yesallmak.
May God keep you safe.
Abû Yûsif... Abû Yûsif ğayrân ktîr...
Abu Youssef... Abu Youssef is very jealous...
Lâ, lâ, ma b-yğîr... b-yḥebbni hayk...
No, no, he doesn't get jealous... he loves me like this...
Halla' 'am es-sawî entî hon kamên şî ismo jibne... farjîna.
Now you are also making something here called cheese... show
us.
Eh 'ala râsî.
Yes, with pleasure.
Farjîna.
Show us.
N-sawî jibne ya'nî...
We make cheese, you know...
Halla' bet-sakbî minno may...
Now you're pouring water from it...
B-şîl l-may minno...
I remove the water from it...
Şlon 'ameltî l-jibne? Eḥkî-lî şlon saweytîha?
How did you make the cheese? Tell me how you made it?
Ḥaṭeyt dawa bas.
I just put rennet in it.
Ya'nî ğaleytî l-ḥalîb?
You mean, did you boil the milk?
Lâ! Lak 'a-l-bâred!
No! On cold!
'A-l-bâred!
On cold!
'A-l-bâred lakan. Jâbûn min el-ğanam w sawaynâha.
On cold, of course. They brought it from the sheep and we
made it.
W ḥaṭeyt dawa, w ğaṭayt.
And I put rennet, and covered it.
بعد ما حطوا، بشيل المي منه، المي كثير بعدين بحطه بشغلة وحط
شوية حبة بركة...
After putting it, I remove the water from it, a lot of
water, then I put it in something and put a little black
seed...
وبتيبس وبقصوا.
and it dries and I cut it.
يعني بعد شقد الدوا اللي حطيتي فيه ليحول الحليب لجبنة؟
I mean, after how much time does the rennet you put in it
turn the milk into cheese?
هادا... هادا يمكن صار أكتر من ساعة.
This... this maybe took more than an hour.
ساعة بس؟
Just an hour?
إي لازم من زمان أنا حطيت.
Yes, I should have put it a long time ago.
ساعة بدو ليصير جبنة؟
It takes an hour to become cheese?
إي لازم سويته من زمان.
Yes, I should have done it a long time ago.
أيوة.
Yes.
وهي مبارحة أنا سويتها.
And this I made yesterday.
طيب فرجيني.
Okay, show me.
هي الشعارية تبعك؟
This is your vermicelli?
إي لكان.
Yes, of course.
والنملية بسموها؟
And they call it a Namliyyeh (food cupboard)?
إي.
Yes.
هادا شغل مبارحة؟
This is yesterday's work?
إي شغل مبارحة هادا.
Yes, this is yesterday's work.
شو الفرق بين يعني جبنة الماعز وجبنة الغنم؟
What is the difference between, I mean, goat cheese and
sheep cheese?
جبنة ماعز... شوية هيك يعني ما بتصير كتير.
Goat cheese... it's a bit like this, I mean it doesn't yield
a lot.
الا إذا معو غنم يعني بتصير كتير إيوا.
Unless it has sheep milk with it, then it yields a lot, yes.
يعني بتصير وافرة.
I mean, it becomes abundant.
سميكة يعني كتير سماكتو.
Thick, I mean its thickness is a lot.
هي إيشو هي؟
What is this?
خالة أم يوسف.
Aunt Um Youssef.
هي جونية بقولوا.
They call this a Jouniyyeh.
جونية لايش هي؟
A Jouniyyeh for what?
هيك كان أول زمان يروحوا ع الحويش بالبرية بيحطوا معه...
بيحطوا حويش.
Like this, in the old days they used to go to gather herbs
in the wild, they put with it... they put herbs.
وشغل البيت يعني خضرة ما خضرة شغلة هيك.
And house work, I mean vegetables, whatever vegetables,
things like that.
بس هادا مو شغلنا نحن ما منسوي شغلات هيك، ما منعرف.
But this is not our work, we don't do things like this, we
don't know.
هدول تبعات حلب بيجوا لعنا سووا النا وجابوا.
Those people from Aleppo come to us, they made it for us and
brought it.
هادا شو هادا؟ كرسي؟
What is this? A chair?
هادا كرسي مشان تحت الصينية تحت الصينية.
This is a chair for under the tray, under the tray.
بتحطوها تحت الصينية؟
You put it under the tray?
هي قديمة... هي لسا جد أمي سواها.
This is old... this, my mother's grandfather made it.
جد أمك هادا؟
Your mother's grandfather?
هادا... إيوا حنان حسكو.
This... yes, Hanan Hasko.
تحت الصينية بتحطوه؟
Under the tray you put it?
إيوا.
Yes.
وهي... هي جديدة ابني سواها.
And this... this is new, my son made it.
ابنك سواها، هي حديثة.
Your son made it, this is modern.
إي هي حديثة.
Yes, this is modern.
طيب هاللبسية.. هاللبسية... هادا التوب اللي لبستيه حالياً.
Okay, this clothing.. this clothing... this dress that you
are wearing currently.
هادا بقولوا روب كردي.
This, they call it a Kurdish robe.
هادا تراث هو؟
This is heritage?
إي تراثنا... تراثنا إي.
Yes, our heritage... our heritage, yes.
في كل عفرين هيك؟ ولا في شي بميزه بشران؟
Is it like this in all of Afrin? Or is there something that
distinguishes it in Sharran?
لا.. كل عفرين، نسوان عفرين كلهم هيك.
No.. all of Afrin, the women of Afrin are all like this.
كلهم هيك...
All like this...
وع راسك؟
And on your head?
كمان نفس الشي... شاشية بقولولها.
Also the same thing... they call it Shashiyeh.
شو اسمه ع راسك؟ شاشية؟
What is it called on your head? Shashiyeh?
شاشية.
Shashiyeh.
خالتي الله يعطيك العافية، هلا إنتي شهيتينا ريحة الأكل اللي
هون.
Auntie, may God give you health, now you made us crave the
smell of the food here.
بس مو ريحتها طيبة، ان شاء الله بيطلع كويسة.
But isn't its smell good? God willing it will turn out well.
ان شاء الله... الله يعطيكم العافية.
God willing... may God give you health.
وأنا بدي أصير بالتلفزيون؟ والله عيب من هالعمر بعد هالعمر
كمان...
And I am going to be on television? By God, it's shameful at
this age, after this age too...
لا لا هلا بشوفوكي الشباب والصبايا ولادك ان شاء الله
وقرايبينك.
No no, now the young men and women, your children God
willing, and your relatives will see you.
والله ان شاء الله، مشان ولادي والله مشان يشوفوني.
By God, God willing, for my children, by God, so they see
me.
الله يخليك... الله يطول عمرك. السلام عليكم.
May God keep you... may God prolong your life. Peace be upon
you.
وعليكم السلام، أهلاً وسهلاً، الله يعافيكم يا رب.
And upon you be peace, welcome, may God give you health, O
Lord.
[Music]
بهالفقرة القصيرة رح نتجول معكم بالسيارة بشوارع شران،
In this short segment, we will take a tour with you by car
in the streets of Sharran,
اللي هي مركز ناحية شران متل ما حكينا في البداية.
which is the center of Sharran sub-district, as we mentioned
in the beginning.
لاحظوا البلدة مبنية فعلاً على السفوح الغربية والجنوبية لهضبة
كلسية،
Notice the town is actually built on the western and
southern slopes of a limestone plateau,
وبيوتها كلها متوجهة نحو الغرب والجنوب.
and its houses are all oriented towards the west and south.
البلد فيها عراقة كبيرة، واليوم عم تغص بالسوريين من مختلف
المناطق السورية
The town has a great heritage, and today it is crowded with
Syrians from various Syrian regions
بسبب موجات التهجير الكبيرة اللي شهدتها سوريا.
due to the large waves of displacement that Syria witnessed.
ففيها سوريين أصليين من أهالي البلدة من الأكراد وأيضاً من بعض
العرب،
So there are original Syrians from the town's residents,
Kurds, and also some Arabs,
وفيها أيضاً سوريين مهجرين من كل المحافظات السورية؛ شام وحلب
وحمص وإدلب ودرعا.
and there are also displaced Syrians from all Syrian
governorates; Damascus, Aleppo, Homs, Idlib, and Daraa.
انتشار الأبنية... بسبب انتشار الأبنية الحديثة على أطراف
البلدة الغربية والشمالية،
The spread of buildings... due to the spread of modern
buildings on the western and northern outskirts of the town,
أبنية طابقية على النموذج الحديث فيلات.
multi-story buildings in the modern villa style.
نحن ماشيين الآن يعني في الطريق الرئيسي
We are driving now, I mean, on the main road
اللي يصل ما بين طريق حلب... عفواً من طريق عفرين - اعزاز
which connects the Aleppo road... excuse me, from the Afrin
- Azaz road
يصل إلى شران شمالاً باتجاه الحدود التركية.
it reaches Sharran to the north towards the Turkish borders.
شايفين قديش يعني البلد حلوة وجميلة،
You see how much, I mean, the town is sweet and beautiful,
الطرق العريضة والأشجار الموجودة على طرفي الطريق والأبنية
الحديثة اللي إلها طابع أيضاً... طابع عريق وجميل.
the wide roads and the trees on both sides of the road, and
the modern buildings that also have a character... an
ancient and beautiful character.
يعني الرونق الجمالي موجود بقوة في هالبلدة.
I mean, the aesthetic splendor is strongly present in this
town.
[Music]
لاحظوا الطبيعة يعني الريفية الزراعية للبلدة واضحة تماماً،
Notice the rural, agricultural nature of the town is
completely clear,
خراف وأغنام موجودة في بيدر القرية.
sheep and flocks are present in the village's threshing
floor.
البيوت إلها شكل... إلها شكل يعني البيوت الأفقية اللي مبنية
كلها على شكل بيوت عربية
The houses have a shape... they have a shape, I mean,
horizontal houses that are all built in the form of Arab
houses
وليست على شكل بيوت طابقية إلا ما خلا بعض يعني الأبنية
الحديثة في الجهة الشمالية الغربية.
and not in the form of multi-story houses, except for some,
I mean, modern buildings in the northwestern side.
أيضاً واضحة كروم الزيتون والعنب على يسارنا،
Also clear are the olive and grape orchards on our left,
على يميننا بيدر الضيعة.
on our right is the village's threshing floor.
متل ما قلت لكم رح نوصل لساحة القرية اللي هي أمام الجامع اللي
عمره 50 سنة،
As I told you, we will reach the village square, which is in
front of the mosque that is 50 years old,
واللي أيضاً هي على طرفها اليسار... المضافة القديمة اللي كانت
للآغا...
and which is also on its left side... the old guest house
that belonged to the Agha...
الآغا تبع القرية والمختار فيما بعد.
The Agha of the village and the Mukhtar later on.
واللي كانت تقام فيها الأفراح والاجتماعات العامة وتصدر فيها
القرارات المهمة ويمكن أيضاً
And where weddings and public meetings used to be held, and
important decisions issued, and maybe also
كان يصير فيها سهرات وأيضاً يصير فيها اجتماع للعزاءات لأهالي
القرية.
evening gatherings would happen there, and also gatherings
for condolences for the village residents.
انتهت جولتنا ببلدة شران واللي هي مركز ناحية من نواحي منطقة
عفرين بشمال غرب حلب.
Our tour has ended in the town of Sharran, which is a sub-
district center of the Afrin region in northwestern Aleppo.
رح ننتظر منكم تفاعلاتكم واقتراحاتكم للحلقات القادمة على صفحة
الفيس وأيضاً صفحة اليوتيوب الخاصة بالبرنامج.
We will wait for your interactions and suggestions for the
upcoming episodes on the Facebook page and also the YouTube
page for the program.
رح نكون معكم بإذن الله تعالى في الأسبوع القادم بحلقة جديدة
من بلدة أو قرية سورية أخرى حبيبة لمتابعة برنامجنا.
We will be with you, God Almighty willing, next week with a
new episode from another beloved Syrian town or village to
follow our program.
تابعوا صفحة الفيس الخاصة بالقناة أو موقعنا على الإنترنت
halabtodaytv.net.
Follow the channel's Facebook page or our website
السلام عليكم ورحمة الله وبركاته.
Peace, mercy, and blessings of God be upon you.
[Music]